# **Christopher Tastad** | Letter

**L** (612) 817–7989 • ☑ ctastad@gmail.com • **O** ctastad • **in** ctastad

HR Department December 18, 2019

ADDRESS CITY, STATE ZIP

To Whom It May Concern,

I am interested in applying for the \*\*\* position with \*\*\*. With my background, I provide a unique blend of content knowledge, technical analysis, and relevant experience that make me a strong fit for the role. I have brought this aptitude together through a few core principles which I have applied in a diverse range of settings. Critical thinking and objectivity guide my approach; independence and competency carry to completion; and an attraction towards establishing effective systems elevates outcomes.

My first and most prominent experience was in stem cell development with a disease model of muscular dystrophy. As a research associate in The Stem Cell Institute, I worked in a central role through independent project coordination, grant and manuscript writing, lab member training, and overall lab management. While serving in this position, I employed strict research methodology and analysis to produce publication quality data. With that, I often presented and defended my efforts to both my primary investigator and the broader scientific community. The product of this work led to several co-authorships in high impact journals as well as being awarded individual grant monies with contributions to lab-wide grants.

Additionally, in recent history, I have focused in the study of handling large data sets, particularly in Bioinformatics. As an integrative field, I've brought my medical content knowledge forward with the development of advanced skill sets in statistical and computational modeling. By developing expertise in this area, I have drastically expanded the nature, flexibility, and application of the analytics capabilities that underline my scientific training. Most importantly, my ability to work with large data sets has become subject agnostic and can translate to any intensive technical task, all of which would be well suited to \*\*\*'s business objectives.

Taken together, I would appreciate further consideration and an opportunity to interview with \*\*\* for the \*\*\* role. Please feel free to contact me at (612) 817–7989 or ctastad@gmail.com.

Sincerely,

**Christopher Tastad** 

Attached: Resume

## **Christopher Tastad** | Resume

**L** (612) 817–7989 • ☑ ctastad@gmail.com • **O** ctastad • **in** ctastad

#### **Education**

Bioinformatics, MS Minneapolis, MN

University of Minnesota, Bioinformatics and Computational Biology

Dec 2019

Capstone: Copy number variation in ovarian cancer from single cell and whole exome sequencing data.

Biochemistry, BS Minneapolis, MN

University of Minnesota, College of Biological Sciences

May 2011

#### **Skills**

Languages: R, BASH, LATEX, SQL, HTML, CSS, XML

Platforms: Linux, git, NGINX, APACHE, HPC, virtualization, docker, Relational Databases, Oracle, wordpress

Packages: rmarkdown, shiny, ggplot2, dplyr, isonlite, DT

**Genomics**: samtools, bwa-mem, bedtools, Seurat, VarScan2, Excavator, DNAcopy, parallel, SummarizedExperiment **Statistics**: Hypothesis testing, Simple/Multiple/Poisson Regression, A/B Testing, Contingency Testing, ANOVA, Survival Analysis, K-means, PCA, K-nearest neighbor, SVM, Bayesian Networks, Functional Linkage Networks **Benchwork**: DNA/RNA/protein isolation and analysis, western blotting, PCR, ELISA, luciferase, immunostaining,

histology, epigenetic analysis, FACS, mammalian cell culture

#### **Experience**

#### **Graduate Research Assistant**

Department of OBGYN, Starr Lab

Minneapolis, MN

May 2019 — Present

- o Executed full rewrite of cancer gene web app: deployed new framework, reduced codebase, removed need for SQL database.
- o Applied bioinformatic focus into copy number variation on a largest of its kind single-cell sequencing human cancer dataset.
- Leveraged comprehensive statistical and computational approach to study whole exome and single cell sequencing cancer data

#### **Load Planning Engineer**

Minneapolis, MN

United Parcel Service, Industrial Engineering

Oct 2018 — Present

- o Primary authority in guiding all load functions for 112 outbound doors; mediating hub, feeder, and engineering priorities.
- o Advance district level interests through industrial engineering technologies for operational, flow, and system analysis.
- o Generate daily cost savings through identification and elimination of trailer runs which average to a value of \$500-1000.

Supervisor Minneapolis, MN

United Parcel Service, Small Sort

Oct 2017 — Oct 2018

- o Managed a team of 35 employees in largest operational unit in the Northern Plains District HQ sort hub.
- o Delivered an immediate 15% production increase to area within first month (representing 40% of daily volume).
- o Developed never-before-seen improvement projects leading to missort elimination and training with disability access.

Package Sorter

Minneapolis, MN

United Parcel Service

June 2017 — Oct 2017

Graduate Research Assistant

Minneapolis, MN

National Marrow Donor Program, Bioinformatics

Jan 2016 — July 2017

- o Employed scientific method as an investigator in a corporate R&D department with a focus in hematological cancers.
- o Took both basic and clinical approach to investigation in cell therapy, immunology, and organ transplant genetics.
- o Aided development of initiative around IP generation using existing company technology and 13 million patient database.

#### **Biorepository Technician**

New Brighton, MN

National Marrow Donor Program, Research Repository

Sept 2014 — Jan 2016

- o Conducted specimen processing in high-throughput clinical laboratory facility, processing 1000s of samples per day.
- o Managed 300k patient database and long-term storage for FDA and Clinical Trials Network samples using GLP.
- o Contributed to larger registry activities maintaining Be The Match patient-donor sample receiving, storage, and typing.

#### **Banquet and Dining Server**

Minneapolis, MN

Minneapolis Club

Oct 2013 — Sept 2014

- o Performed setup, service, and take down for dining room and banquets ranging from chef's table dinners to events of 500+.
- o Trained in the manner of French service and hospitality to maintain an elite level of accommodation and experience.
- o Participated in maintenance and building upkeep when called upon by external departments.

Co-founder St. Anthony, MN

Face to Face Organics LLC.

July 2012 — Jan 2014

- o Co-founded a personal care products start up that connected social activism with our product and its use.
- o Deployed company's operating software stack on limited budget with minimal upfront cost and sustained overhead.

o Established company systems around e-commerce, CRM, distribution, logistics, accounting, sales tracking, and inventory.

Research Associate

Minneapolis, MN Dec 2007 — Jan 2013

The Stem Cell Institute, Asakura Lab

- o Performed basic science research with a focus in skeletal muscle development, receiving 4 co-authorships.
- Well versed in full spectrum of molecular biology, histology and cell biology wet lab techniques and diagnostics.
- o Authored significant writing efforts for group manuscripts and major grant awards, including a sucessful R01 bid.

Teaching Assistant

St. Paul, MN

University of Minnesota, CBS BIOL2004

Sept 2009 — May 2012

- o Led teaching lab that included an integrative, research-focused curriculum, highlighting significant independent discovery.
- o Consistently called on by course instructor for consultation in the improvement of course materials and curriculum.
- o Received highest rating among all course TAs as indicated by students in post-semester evaluations for 2012 year.

#### Founder, Lobbyist, and Chairman

Minneapolis, MN

Minnesota Student Legislative Coalition

Oct 2009 — July 2012

- o United leaders from all 5 U of M campuses to form the active student lobby, earning the University's endorsement.
- o Directed wide range of issues: education funding, loan rates, textbook pricing, campus safety, and veteran accreditation.
- o Trained and supervised a team that guided the authorship of 4 student-specific bills during 2012 state legislative session.

#### **Personal**

**IT Consultant** 

Hobbies: Racquetball, Self-hosting software, CAD design & 3d printing, Camping, Fishing, Hunting, Reading

Volunteering.

Trinity Lutheran Church of Montevideo

Montevideo, MN July 2017 — Present

Youth Camp Racquetball Coach

Minneapolis, MN

University of Minnesota, Recwell

July 2017 — July 2017

Offiversity of Willinesota, Necwei

**Child Life Specialist** Shriners Hospital for Children

Minneapolis, MN Dec 2008 — May 2013

\_\_\_\_\_

Edina, MN

IT Consultant & Umn Chapter Co-founder

Nov 2008 — July 2011

Ducks Unlimited

Cape Town, South Africa

**Trauma Ward Aide**Student Travel and Exposure South Africa

June 2009 — July 2009

#### **Publications**

- [1] **Tastad, C. T.** and M. Verma. RefSearch: A tool to more accurately identify normalization candidates for RNAseq analysis. *Manuscript in preparation*, 2019.
- [2] Y. Nakamura, Y. Asakura, B. A. Piras, H. Hirai, Tastad, C. T., M. Verma, A. J. Christ, J. Zhang, T. Yamazaki, M. Yoshiyama, and A. Asakura. Increased angiogenesis and improved left ventricular function after transplantation of myoblasts lacking the MyoD gene into infarcted myocardium. *PLoS ONE*, 7(7):e41736, 2012.
- [3] S. Watanabe, H. Hirai, Y. Asakura, **Tastad, C**., M. Verma, C. Keller, J. R. Dutton, and A. Asakura. MyoD gene suppression by Oct4 is required for reprogramming in myoblasts to produce induced pluripotent stem cells. *Stem Cells*, 29(3):505–516, Mar 2011.
- [4] H. Hirai, M. Verma, S. Watanabe, **Tastad, C**., Y. Asakura, and A. Asakura. MyoD regulates apoptosis of myoblasts through microRNA-mediated down-regulation of Pax3. *J. Cell Biol.*, 191(2):347–365, Oct 2010.
- [5] M. Verma, Y. Asakura, H. Hirai, S. Watanabe, Tastad, C., G. H. Fong, M. Ema, J. A. Call, D. A. Lowe, and

A. Asakura. Flt-1 haploinsufficiency ameliorates muscular dystrophy phenotype by developmentally increased vasculature in mdx mice.  $Hum.\ Mol.\ Genet.$ , 19(21):4145–4159, Nov 2010.

### **Awards**

Advocate of the Year: University of Minnesota Alumni Association	Oct, 2012
Spirit of MSA (MVP): Minnesota Student Association	May, 2012
Highest Rated TA: CBS BIOL2004 Lab Students	May, 2012
Research Fellowship: Gregory Marzolf Jr. Foundation	Sept, 2009
Distinct Honor — Presenter's Award: LHI/SCI Building Muscle and Blood Conference	Oct, 2009
Undergraduate Research Opportunity Grant: University of Minnesota	2008, 2009, 2011